<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Temporary Obsessions</title>
    <link>https://temporaryobsessions.github.io/</link>
    <description>Recent content on Temporary Obsessions</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Sun, 15 Apr 2018 12:45:01 -0400</lastBuildDate>
    
        <atom:link href="https://temporaryobsessions.github.io/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>On noticing things while you read</title>
      <link>https://temporaryobsessions.github.io/posts/2018/04/on-noticing-things/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 15 Apr 2018 12:45:01 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://temporaryobsessions.github.io/posts/2018/04/on-noticing-things/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Included with the Coursera course &#34;Learning How to Learn&#34;&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:Take-it-It-s-free&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:Take-it-It-s-free&#34;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; is a video interview between the instructor, Prof. Barbara Oakley, and William Craig Rice, who was then Director of the Division of Education Programs at the National Endowment for the Humanities&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:Rice-passed-away-in-2016&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:Rice-passed-away-in-2016&#34;&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; One thing that struck me in his interview was his approach to reading:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I don&#39;t know that I&#39;m any better at this than another reader would be, because what I start with is just noticing. I was taught this a long time ago that you don&#39;t need to be ready to analyze or make an argument or otherwise elaborate. Just read and when you notice something, mark it. Just noticing is a neutral act, it&#39;s giving your own mind credit for being alive. That&#39;s really important and I mark with a little vertical sign on the margin...you may notice that you&#39;re noticing the same thing over and over again. In which case, I call it a pattern—not an original idea—but you look for patterns.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the interview, the suggestion is clearly aimed at students. It is very good advice for figuring out a paper to write about what you are reading. Beyond that, it is an essential idea for learning and creativity, something that all of us to can put to good use.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In doing an assignment, it is much less stressful to approach a given reading in this way. The first reading is for initial understanding and noticing, not for coming up with a brilliant idea for that paper imminently due. Don&#39;t worry about whether or not you are noticing &#34;the most important things&#34;, or &#34;the killer insight&#34;, or things that just seem dumb. In the moment, it is just you and what your mind is pointing to. What you notice is likely not what everyone else notices, and the points you mark will later help add color and detail in writing your response to the reading.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Marking what you notice is also a terrific way to connect what you are reading with what you already know, helping you to remember what the reading is about. What you notice are the &#34;hooks&#34; in your memory than you can hang the new ideas on. Using these hooks makes it easy to remember essential points about what you have read, because they are meaningful to you. Taking advantage of those meanings is much more effective for memory than simply trying to outline and memorize the key points of a text.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Noticing is also a part of creativity, coming from the collision of ideas. Your unique history, knowledge, and experience primes you to notice things that others won&#39;t, just as they will notice thing you don&#39;t. Being more attentive to the things you notice, even if they seem silly at first, can spark creative ideas in many different directions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What are you supposed to notice? Really, it&#39;s whatever you &lt;em&gt;do&lt;/em&gt; notice. It might be an unfamiliar word, a word used in an unusual way, a striking metaphor, a gap in the explanation. You don&#39;t need to chase them all down; just mark them and continue. Afterwards, you see what patterns you noticed, or ponder the details, or chase down the questions raised.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Part of what struck me about Rice&#39;s comment was simply that I hadn&#39;t heard it put that way before, and I wish I had. He mentions in the video that he was told it long ago. As a student, I would have found it immensely valuable. Most of the advice I had heard about reading was akin to that of Mortimer Adler and Chales Van Doren in &lt;em&gt;How to Read a Book&lt;/em&gt;, which presents a very top-down method of approaching a text. Noticing, on the other hand, is a bottom-up method, letting the creative parts of your brain help with understanding and insight as well. David Mikics, in &lt;em&gt;Slow Reading in a Hurried Age&lt;/em&gt; (which I highly recommend), develops a set of rules for reading literature, and Rule 5 is &#34;Notice beginnings and endings.&#34; This advice is a bit different, meaning that we should pay particular attention to them, but is in the same spirit. And the idea of noticing details permeates the book. Or, perhaps, I encountered the idea, but just hadn&#39;t noticed it before.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Oddly enough, the words &#34;notice&#34; and &#34;note&#34;, which seem so closely related in English, come from different roots in Latin. &#34;notice&#34; is from the Latin &lt;em&gt;nōscere&lt;/em&gt;, meaning &#34;to become acquainted with&#34;, which came from the Greek &lt;em&gt;gnōsis&lt;/em&gt;, meaning knowledge&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:I-took-some-small-liberties-with-the-details-of-the-word-forms-in-the-etymology-but-the-basic-arc-is-correct&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:I-took-some-small-liberties-with-the-details-of-the-word-forms-in-the-etymology-but-the-basic-arc-is-correct&#34;&gt;3&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;, and it came into Middle English via Middle French. The word &#34;note&#34;, on the other hand, comes from the Latin word &lt;em&gt;nota&lt;/em&gt;, meaning a note or mark, which also explains why we have &#34;musical notes&#34; (that is, marks for music), which don&#39;t otherwise seem to have much to do with the kind of notes we take while reading or in a lecture.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;em&gt;Start by noticing.&lt;/em&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;footnotes&#34;&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:Take-it-It-s-free&#34;&gt;DEFINITION NOT FOUND &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:Take-it-It-s-free&#34;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;[return]&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li id=&#34;fn:Rice-passed-away-in-2016&#34;&gt;DEFINITION NOT FOUND &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:Rice-passed-away-in-2016&#34;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;[return]&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li id=&#34;fn:I-took-some-small-liberties-with-the-details-of-the-word-forms-in-the-etymology-but-the-basic-arc-is-correct&#34;&gt;DEFINITION NOT FOUND &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:I-took-some-small-liberties-with-the-details-of-the-word-forms-in-the-etymology-but-the-basic-arc-is-correct&#34;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;[return]&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Time to delete Facebook</title>
      <link>https://temporaryobsessions.github.io/posts/2018/04/deleting-facebook/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 14 Apr 2018 14:12:00 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://temporaryobsessions.github.io/posts/2018/04/deleting-facebook/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Facebook has been in the news a lot lately, in the wake of how Cambridge Analytica used and abused data gathered about Facebook users. Earlier this week, Facebook CEO Mark Zuckerberg testified before Congress.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The big picture is complicated, and unlikely to be resolved any time soon. There are questions about antitrust, free speech, the nature of advertising, how to regulate data privacy. In the U.S., it&#39;s not clear where regulatory jurisdiction lies, or how to construct beneficial regulations that don&#39;t create their own problems in how we can use the Internet well.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, as one of two billion people caught up in how Facebook treats our data, what can I do?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The options are pretty stark. Facebook&#39;s privacy settings are confusing at best, and likely misleading, whether intentionally or not. I cannot be sure of what data Facebook is collecting, how it is doing that, or how that data will be used. I cannot be sure that Facebook would refrain from the using data already collected in some new way that they come up with in the future. I have no insight into what the value of my data to Facebook is, so that I could make a pseudo-economic decision about using Facebook.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For me, Facebook simply has no credibility about respecting the use of the personal data it collects.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Which means the choices are to accept the continuing surveillance without any real control over it, or to quit Facebook altogether.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I don&#39;t really use Facebook that much, because the data issues have been visible for a long time. But I have continued to accept the notion that I might want to, for the communication it in theory provides with my &#34;friends&#34;. And that includes some family members, and I have been loath to cut that off, even as, in actuality, I rarely take advantage of that.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I also know that, whatever I do, I am simply one person out of two billion. Facebook won&#39;t notice. Since I&#39;m not present on Facebook that much, probably few people will notice, much less care.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Nevertheless, it&#39;s time to delete Facebook. Dealing with a huge company I can&#39;t trust is not for me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I can&#39;t say what the right decision for anyone else is. But I think it&#39;s worth thinking hard about whether the value Facebook has for you is more than the unknown cost of what Facebook takes from you.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What is more disturbing is that even deleting your Facebook account doesn&#39;t remove you from its sights, as thousands of web sites are also enlisted in its data collection, whether they realize it or not. Figuring out what I can do about that is the next challenge.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Some respect for Paul Ryan</title>
      <link>https://temporaryobsessions.github.io/posts/2018/04/some-respect-for-paul-ryan/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 13 Apr 2018 11:14:20 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://temporaryobsessions.github.io/posts/2018/04/some-respect-for-paul-ryan/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;A couple of days ago, Paul Ryan announced that he is not running for re-election. Much ink has been spilled, many pixels have been darkened, and unending TV time has been spent talking about the &#34;real reasons&#34; that he is stepping down. Retiring to &#34;spend more time with my family&#34; is such a cliched cover for other motivations that perhaps it&#39;s hard to imagine that it could be real.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ryan has three teenage children, and in his announcement, he said &#34;I know if I spend another term, they will only know me as a weekend father,&#34; and he didn&#39;t want to look back at having missed that time. As a father of three children looking at the trailing end of teenage years, I am grateful for the time I have had to spend with them during that time. I wouldn&#39;t have missed it for anything, not even a powerful job in Washington (not that such a job has ever been in my career plans).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Are there other reasons? Perhaps. In reality, there always are. The job doesn&#39;t seem to be much fun now. It seems impossible to get anything done in Congress. But does that mean we can&#39;t (or shouldn&#39;t) take his statement at face value?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Many have questioned his timing as well. He spoke to that in his announcement: that running for another term, then resigning, would not be honest with the people of his district. He is, after all, a Congressional representative from a particular district. I think we all expect our representatives (and senators) to remember where they are from, and who they represent, even as they conduct the business of the nation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In other words, Ryan has told us about two central values: his family and his responsibility to his constituents. Living up to those values deserves respect, even if we disagree with his actions as a Representative and as Speaker.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And, if they aren&#39;t the real reasons, aren&#39;t they at least values that we would want our political leaders to live by?&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Emacs: Default content for a blog post</title>
      <link>https://temporaryobsessions.github.io/posts/2018/04/emacs-auto-insert/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 12 Apr 2018 11:51:13 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://temporaryobsessions.github.io/posts/2018/04/emacs-auto-insert/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I wanted to configure Emacs to automatically insert a template for particular kinds of files, but only in certain directories. All of the machinery for this exists, but it doesn&#39;t quite seem to be all connected together.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The starting point is &lt;code&gt;auto-insert&lt;/code&gt;, which provides a simple template mechanism to insert text into a file when it is first created. The template language can also execute Lisp expressions, making it possible to insert dynamic data as well.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here&#39;s the basic setup for an org-mode template for a blog post using Hugo (which is why we have to fix up the timezone in the date string):&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-emacs-lisp&#34;&gt;(define-auto-insert &#39;org-mode
  &#39;(&amp;quot;Blog post header&amp;quot;
    &amp;quot;#+TITLE: &amp;quot; - &amp;quot;\n&amp;quot;
    &amp;quot;#+DATE: &amp;quot;
    (format-time-string &amp;quot;%FT%T%z&amp;quot;)
    ;; Fix the timezone format for Hugo
    -2
    &amp;quot;:00&amp;quot;
    &amp;quot;\n\n&amp;quot;))
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This assumes that &lt;code&gt;auto-insert-mode&lt;/code&gt; is enabled, and that &lt;code&gt;auto-insert-query&lt;/code&gt; is configured to ask for confirmation, since I don&#39;t want to do this in all Org files.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&#39;ll add the per-directory part later.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Podcast list as of 4/11/2018</title>
      <link>https://temporaryobsessions.github.io/posts/2018/04/podcast-list/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 11 Apr 2018 10:52:46 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://temporaryobsessions.github.io/posts/2018/04/podcast-list/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Here&#39;s a list of the podcasts I currently have in my rotation, within the constraint of getting through them in a week. No claims about these being the &#34;best&#34; podcasts, just what I&#39;m listening to now.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://99percentinvisible.org/&#34; title=&#34;99% Invisible&#34;&gt;99% Invisible&lt;/a&gt;: A podcast about design, mostly invisible, that shapes our experience of the world. Hosted by Roman Mars, who has possibly the best podcast voice in podcasting.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.akimbo.me/&#34; title=&#34;Akimbo&#34;&gt;Akimbo&lt;/a&gt;: From Seth Godin, who describes it as &#34;a podcast about our culture and about how we can change it. About seeing what&#39;s happening and choosing to do something.&#34; Exactly.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.theallusionist.org/&#34; title=&#34;The Allusionist&#34;&gt;The Allusionist&lt;/a&gt;: A podcast about the language, from the other side of the pond. Delightful.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.nytimes.com/podcasts/the-daily&#34; title=&#34;The Daily&#34;&gt;The Daily&lt;/a&gt;: From the New York Times. Each weekday morning, a look behind one of the important headlines of the day, with host Michael Barbaro talking to a Times journalist who is covering that story. It brings out of the personality of the reporter and the depth of what they know about those stories and the background.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://blog.cognitect.com/cognicast/&#34; title=&#34;Cognicast&#34;&gt;Cognicast&lt;/a&gt;: A podcast from Cognitect, a software consulting company, about software and the people who make it. Technically, the show draws mostly on the Clojure software world, but many of the stories are about bigger issues in software engineering, engineering, and life.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.imaginaryworldspodcast.org/&#34; title=&#34;Imaginary Worlds&#34;&gt;Imaginary Worlds&lt;/a&gt;: Eric Molinsky&#39;s bi-weekly podcast about the genres of science fiction and fantasy, especially about how they impossible stories tell us so much about ourselves.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.slate.com/articles/podcasts/lexicon_valley.html&#34; title=&#34;Lexicon Valley&#34;&gt;Lexicon Valley&lt;/a&gt;: A Slate podcast about language, hosted by John McWhorter, a professor who teaches linguistics, philosophy, and music at Columbia. Endlessly fascinating.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.wnycstudios.org/shows/notetoself&#34; title=&#34;Note to Self&#34;&gt;Note to Self&lt;/a&gt;: a terrific podcast from WYNC looking at the ways we use technology now and how that affects ordinary life.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.wnycstudios.org/shows/otm/&#34; title=&#34;On The Media&#34;&gt;On The Media&lt;/a&gt;: Another WNYC program, looking at how the media looks at the world and tells us about it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://radioopensource.org/&#34; title=&#34;Open Source with Christopher Lydon&#34;&gt;Open Source with Christopher Lydon&lt;/a&gt;: A podcast (and radio program) about &#34;arts, ideas, and politics&#34;, hosted by Christopher Lydon, who has been a fixture on the Boston media scene for decades. He has an astonishing ability to make anything interesting, and talk about it smartly in depth.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.npr.org/programs/wait-wait-dont-tell-me/&#34; title=&#34;Wait Wait...Don&#39;t Tell Me!&#34;&gt;Wait Wait...Don&#39;t Tell Me!&lt;/a&gt;: NPR&#39;s comedy news quiz show. It&#39;s got the best roundup of news I hear in a week.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.radiotopia.fm/podcasts/trump-con-law&#34; title=&#34;What Trump Can Teach Us About Con Law&#34;&gt;What Trump Can Teach Us About Con Law&lt;/a&gt;: Whatever one&#39;s political leanings, I think we can agree that the President has given us all a chance to learn about points of the US Constitution we haven&#39;t thought much about before. This show, hosted by constitution law professor Elizabeth Joh and the aforementioned Roman Mars, explores those points for those of us who aren&#39;t lawyers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&#39;d like to have more on the list, when time permits.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I also use &lt;a href=&#34;https://huffduffer.com/&#34; title=&#34;Huffduffer&#34;&gt;Huffduffer&lt;/a&gt;, a marvelous web tool for putting an audio program from a web site into a podcast feed for you. It&#39;s great for listening to random bits of audio from around the web.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Coming back to podcasts</title>
      <link>https://temporaryobsessions.github.io/posts/2018/04/coming-back-to-podcasts/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 10 Apr 2018 12:04:07 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://temporaryobsessions.github.io/posts/2018/04/coming-back-to-podcasts/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Yesterday I wrote about &lt;a href=&#34;https://temporaryobsessions.github.io/posts/giving-up-podcasts/&#34; title=&#34;giving up podcasts&#34;&gt;giving up podcasts&lt;/a&gt;. For a long time, I liked the feeling of a less-cluttered mind, which seemed to be correlated with taking that step. But I still missed them. Partly it was from the random incompletions of listening to the radio in the car. Mostly it was missing some of my favorite voices, bringing some perspectives that I don&#39;t otherwise get to hear.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A couple of weeks ago, I started bringing some back, slowly. Adding one at a time, catching up on the last three episodes, just to see if I still wanted to hear that voice. My current rule is to add only as many as I can get through in a week. I don&#39;t want to re-create the backlog, with its pressure to listen, that I had before. And I&#39;m trying to keep a little bit of diversity of voice and topic in the collection.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So far, it seems to be working. It&#39;s not stressful, and I&#39;m enjoying it, without giving up chances for my mind to wander and think about my own work as well.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The quiet time is still important, so I&#39;m trying to leave plenty of opportunity for that.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We&#39;ll see how it goes.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>On giving up podcasts</title>
      <link>https://temporaryobsessions.github.io/posts/2018/04/giving-up-podcasts/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 09 Apr 2018 10:39:06 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://temporaryobsessions.github.io/posts/2018/04/giving-up-podcasts/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Last fall, I gave up podcasts. Cold turkey.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It was Manoush&#39;s fault. &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.manoushz.com/&#34; title=&#34;Manoush Zomorodi&#34;&gt;Manoush Zomorodi&lt;/a&gt; hosts the WYNC podcast &#34;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.wnycstudios.org/shows/notetoself&#34; title=&#34;Note to Self&#34;&gt;Note to Self&lt;/a&gt;&#34;, about life with modern technology. She did a series on the show did called &#34;Bored and Brilliant&#34; that turned into a &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.manoushz.com/book/&#34; title=&#34;book with the same name.&#34;&gt;book with the same name.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the series, she posed a set of challenges to experience personal technology differently. The last one: delete the app on your phone that is always grabbing your attention. For some, it&#39;s Facebook. For others, Twitter. Or maybe Two Dots.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For me, it was podcasts. Over several years, I had amassed a large collection of podcast subscriptions, and I listened all the time. In the car, doing dishes, on a walk, in the gym, working in the yard. If I wasn&#39;t doing requiring focused mental attention, I was listening, to an eclectic collection that ranged over a wide range of topics. All of them were interesting: stimulating ideas to ponder, things to think about, political issues to be outraged over.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then, last September, I was outside cleaning up the yard for fall and listening to Brooke Gladstone (of WNYC&#39;s &#34;On the Media&#34; show) interview Manoush after the book came out. She talked about the Bored &amp; Brilliant challenges. And I realized that Overcast was my problem app.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Don&#39;t get me wrong. Overcast is a great app, and podcasts are great. But it was time to take a break.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I didn&#39;t delete it, because I didn&#39;t want to lose the subscription list if I decided to come back. But I did exile it from the home screen on my phone to avoid seeing it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After the interview was open, I stopped listening to podcasts. Complete stop. My plan was to try it, as Manoush had challenged, for a week. Which turned into two. And then months.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first couple of days I was going crazy. I had to take a 45-minute bus ride to the airport for a sudden trip. I can&#39;t read on a bus, so I usually listen to podcasts. Instead, I stared out the window. Taking a walk, I let my mind wander as I looked at the landscape. In the car, if I put on the radio (which wasn&#39;t always), I put on NPR or (gasp!) commercial radio. I felt like something was wrong.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There&#39;s a weird effect of going back to listening to radio programs that are also available as podcasts: the radio doesn&#39;t pause when you get out of the car.&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:1&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:1&#34;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; That took a little getting used to.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But then something started to happen. Over the next few days, I started to feel calmer. Maybe more focused at times--it&#39;s hard to tell. A lot more mind wandering. Too much time, it seems, with music running through my head that I can&#39;t quite seem to control. Perhaps a few extra ideas out of nowhere. Nothing earth-shattering, but occasional creative solutions to small problems. I mentally composed a note about this, which is, much later, turning into this post, on a walk.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For the most, I had thought that the podcasts were a good way of getting exposed to new ideas and information during otherwise mindless time. The experience of stopping showed me that, perhaps, they were getting in the way of my own ideas and putting them together with others.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It&#39;s not new to say that the mind-wandering time is essential for creativity, or for having the capacity to focus intently at other times. Quitting podcasts gave me a direct experience for the difference, and I like the way it feels.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;footnotes&#34;&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:1&#34;&gt;Actually, a long time ago, some colleagues and I built a system that stored the previous 24 hours of our local NPR station, so you could pause the radio in your office. This was well before DVRs or podcasts, and it completely changed the radio experience, as well as startling some visitors at times. One consequence was that as you walked down our row of offices, you might hear NPR playing from different times of the day! &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:1&#34;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;[return]&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>On being intuitively obvious</title>
      <link>https://temporaryobsessions.github.io/posts/2018/04/intuitively-obvious/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 08 Apr 2018 12:49:00 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://temporaryobsessions.github.io/posts/2018/04/intuitively-obvious/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;A long time ago, when I was an undergraduate, it was common to hear someone say that  idea, usually a statement in mathematics, was “intuitively obvious”. I say “statement”, because not everything so labeled was necessarily true. But it was almost always said with irony or sarcasm, as if the phrase was by then overused, cliche, and amusing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Recently, however, I happened across a seemingly non-ironic use, in the book &lt;em&gt;Syntactic Structures&lt;/em&gt; by Noam Chomsky.&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:5&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:5&#34;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Consider for example the pair of sentences&lt;br/&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
(103) (i)  John knew the boy studying in the library.&lt;br/&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&amp;nbsp; &amp;nbsp; &amp;nbsp; &amp;nbsp; &amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;(ii)  John found the boy studying in the library.&lt;br/&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
It is intuitively obvious that these sentences have different grammatical structure (this becomes clear, for example, when we attempt to add “not running around in the streets” to (103)), but I do not believe that within the level of phrase structure grounds can be found for analyzing them into different constituents.&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:1&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:1&#34;&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finding this in a published book started me wondering about the origin of the phrase. With Google Books, we can poke around a bit.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The oldest use in a book that I could find is from &lt;em&gt;A Demonstration of Necessary Connexion&lt;/em&gt; by John Fearn, in a philosophical/theological argument against David Hume.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
All, therefore, that we have to do, to prove, &lt;em&gt;by that abstract argument&lt;/em&gt;, the being of A SELF-EXISTENT
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
FIRST CAUSE &lt;em&gt;of all things&lt;/em&gt;, is, to produce “an instance wherein one event must follow from another as an infallible consequence.”
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
That the first proposal of such a proof should excite as much incredulity as surprise, is to be expected. But,fortunately,the truth of the propositions is so intuitively obvious, that the slightest attention must discern t; and, from the nature of the subject, it is to be hoped that attention will be
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
afforded to them by every person who is in the least degree interested in general knowledge.&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:2&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:2&#34;&gt;3&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Other early works that show up mostly seem to be concerned with philosophy or theology. The first reference I found specifically about mathematics comes via the first volume of Charles Richardson&#39;s &lt;em&gt;A New Dictionary of the English Dictionary&lt;/em&gt;, published in 1836.&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:3&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:3&#34;&gt;4&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; In his dictionary, Richardson cited Dugald Stewart&#39;s &lt;em&gt;Elements of the Philosophy of the Human Mind&lt;/em&gt; &lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:4&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:4&#34;&gt;5&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; from 1822, which includes the statement “The truth of mathematical axioms has always been supposed to be intuitively obvious.” But Stewart&#39;s work is ultimately, in fact, about philosophy, not mathematics.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&#39;m a bit suspicious about how far this gets us, because it took some focused queries to find the Chomsky quotation above; it didn&#39;t show up in the initial search results. &lt;a href=&#34;https://books.google.com/ngrams/graph?content=intuitively+obvious&amp;amp;year_start=1600&amp;amp;year_end=1825&amp;amp;corpus=15&amp;amp;smoothing=3&amp;amp;share=&amp;amp;direct_url=t1%253B%252Cintuitively%2520obvious%253B%252Cc0#t1%253B%252Cintuitively%2520obvious%253B%252Cc1&#34; title=&#34;Google Ngrams&#34;&gt;Google Ngrams&lt;/a&gt; shows the phrase first showing up in 1790, but I couldn&#39;t persuade it to show me the actual citation, and Wired has previously reported on &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.wired.com/2015/10/pitfalls-of-studying-language-with-google-ngram/&#34; title=&#34;The Pitfalls of Using Google Ngram to Study Language&#34;&gt;The Pitfalls of Using Google Ngram to Study Language&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Chomsky&#39;s &lt;em&gt;Syntactic Structures&lt;/em&gt; is, in large part, brought some mathematical methods of reasoning to linguistics, at a time when much linguistic thinking still relied on intuitions about language and how it works. But in the time between &lt;em&gt;Syntactic Structures&lt;/em&gt; and the early 1980s, I suspect that the ironic usage of “intuitively obvious” emerged as intuition fell away as a basis for knowledge. Of course, intuition is often essential for new discoveries and insights in science and mathematics, but the intuition must be confirmed (or disproved) by other, more reliable, means. In any case, what is “obvious” to one person is often not “obvious” to another.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As one might expect, the trail on historical usage on a term like this usually peters out into an ocean of antecedents, many of which we will never recover. Nevertheless, it seems interesting to find records of a time when “intuitively obvious” was used earnestly, without the sarcastic flavor it often carries today.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;footnotes&#34;&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:5&#34;&gt;Although I do not rule out that the possibility that Chomsky slipped it in with a wink.] &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:5&#34;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;[return]&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li id=&#34;fn:1&#34;&gt;From Noam Chomsky, &lt;em&gt;Syntactic Structures&lt;/em&gt;, Mouton, 1957 (Eleventh printing, 1975, p. 81). &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:1&#34;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;[return]&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li id=&#34;fn:2&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://books.google.com/books?hl=en&amp;lr=&amp;id=No1bAAAAMAAJ&amp;oi=fnd&amp;pg=PA1&amp;dq=%2522intuitively+obvious%2522&amp;ots=GmKevu5vUV&amp;sig=ijR2XDMQex81o2td4NHg7kETxzo#v=onepage&amp;q=%2522intuitively%2520obvious%2522&amp;f=false&#34;&gt;A Demonstration of Necessary Connexion - John Fearn&lt;/a&gt; (London: Longman, Hurst, 1815, p. 5). &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:2&#34;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;[return]&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li id=&#34;fn:3&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://books.google.com/books?id=wH9FAAAAcAAJ&amp;pg=RA1-PA1148&amp;dq=%2522intuitively+obvious%2522&amp;hl=en&amp;sa=X&amp;ved=0ahUKEwjf56G2lavaAhUk54MKHYyvDxM4FBDoAQgyMAI#v=onepage&amp;q=%2522intuitively%2520obvious%2522&amp;f=false&#34;&gt;A New English Dictionary of the English Language: A to K - Charles Richardson&lt;/a&gt; (London, William Pickering, 1836). Compared to Samual Johnson, Richardson included a larger and wider range of quotations from published literature along with definitions, and it has been said that Richardson&#39;s dictionary was a large part of the inspiration for the Oxford English Dictionary. On the other, Richardson was of the school that each word had exactly one meaning. &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:3&#34;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;[return]&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li id=&#34;fn:4&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://archive.org/details/elementsphiloso13stewgoog&#34;&gt;Elements of the philosophy of the human mind&lt;/a&gt; by Dugald Stewart (Albany:E. and E. Hosford, 1822). Interestingly, the scanned copy I found at the Internet Archive was scanned from Harvard&#39;s library, and was the copy “From the books in the homestead of Sarah Orne Jewett at South Berwick, Maine”, which brings things back to reading her novel &lt;em&gt;The Country of the Pointed Firs&lt;/em&gt; as an undergrad, although I don&#39;t recall the phrase “intuitively obvious” ever being used in that literature class. &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:4&#34;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;[return]&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>What if everyone gets over the bar?</title>
      <link>https://temporaryobsessions.github.io/posts/2018/04/everyone-over-the-bar/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 07 Apr 2018 12:00:33 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://temporaryobsessions.github.io/posts/2018/04/everyone-over-the-bar/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Suppose a school had a basketball team, and the coach of the team worked to challenge every player to be the best they could be. Maybe even better. The players developed skills at all positions, and everyone played. There was no regular, default starting lineup, because the players could be selected at random to form a group of five who could play together, and win games, as a team. The players are excited to be there, they work hard together, and they cheer each other on. And they all get to play.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And they win a lot of their games. Often a championship. Not alwayshttps://gohugo.io/content-management/formats/, but mostly.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;How would we think about that coach? As a genius? Maybe it seems impossible, or that couldn&#39;t possibly the right way to coach. But we probably wouldn&#39;t argue much with the results: a team that works hard, values every player, and wins. What&#39;s bad about that.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Nothing, of course.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now, let&#39;s imagine a math teacher at a different school. One who sets a high standard of excellence and challenges every student. One who works exceedingly hard to build a team of math students, who cheer each other on, who help each other learn. At the end of the year, every one of those students scores at the top of whatever standard math assessment is current for the school. And every one of them gets an A.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But wait, we might say. Grade inflation! The teacher is just handing out the top grades. You can&#39;t possibly have a math class where everyone gets an A. Where&#39;s the bell curve? Who is at the top?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Are these cases really that different? The methods seem to be pretty much the same: set a high bar and work like hell to get everyone over it. They do it as a team. They get everyone there, together. And, both cases, we would be happy with the outcome.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Except for this little nagging feeling that everyone getting an A isn&#39;t right.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Maybe that&#39;s the problem we have: the feeling that students have to be ranked. That for some to succeed, some must fail.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Which approach actually serves the students better?&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>That great idea I had</title>
      <link>https://temporaryobsessions.github.io/posts/2018/04/that-great-idea-i-had/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 06 Apr 2018 11:22:56 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://temporaryobsessions.github.io/posts/2018/04/that-great-idea-i-had/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;This is a post about a great idea I had while I was out for a walk yesterday.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Unfortunately, it&#39;s only &lt;em&gt;about&lt;/em&gt; the idea. I&#39;m not exploring the idea itself.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Because I forgot it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I forgot it in the fewer than ten minutes it took me to get home. Or maybe it was because I was too close to home, and the process of going into the house and talking to my family pushed it out of my mind.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It was a pretty good idea. Maybe not an actual great idea, but not bad. Something worth writing about. A little evolution in my thinking on something or other. Or maybe it wasn&#39;t actually that good, and I would have ended up discarding it without writing a word about it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But I didn&#39;t write it down. Or ask Siri to remind me about it. Why didn&#39;t I?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Friction and hubris. Friction, in that it was cold outside yesterday. I had gloves on. As it happened, I did have a notebook and pen in my pocket, but they were hard to get to. The phone was similarly inconvenient. It would have meant standing by the side of the road along an awkward curve, feeling exposed, unsafe, and a bit silly standing there scribbling a note. Hubris, in that I thought it was so good and clear that I would remember it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ten minutes later, it was gone. My mind had moved on.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It might come back again. Ideas often do. But not always. Sometimes they move on. Maybe the idea will move on to someone else---Elizabeth Gilbert has written about that.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But I do know that more ideas will come. Some not as good, some better. Mostly just different. Or similar.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Next time, I will try harder to capture the idea. But if I don&#39;t, I&#39;ll try to get the one after that.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Who do you want to be?</title>
      <link>https://temporaryobsessions.github.io/posts/2018/04/students-who-do-you-want-to-be/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 05 Apr 2018 11:48:13 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://temporaryobsessions.github.io/posts/2018/04/students-who-do-you-want-to-be/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;A high school principal I know told a story told to her by another principal. It was approximately:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
A lot of students ask me what it takes to get into the National Honor Society. But one student stood out for asking a different question: &#34;What is it like to &lt;em&gt;be&lt;/em&gt; a member of the National Honor Society?&#34; (emphasis mine)
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This question bounced in my mind off something else I heard recently, on a college tour with one of my daughters. There, one of the admissions officials said something like:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Most of our students share the following three characteristics (what they were doesn&#39;t really matter). You don&#39;t have to have all three of these, or two of them, or even one. But you should want to be around people like that.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For students looking at colleges, or, in fact, for any of us looking at a new job with a new organization, or a new role of any kind, these questions provide a valuable way of thinking about what to do:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;What are the characteristics of the people involved?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Does that represent the kind of person I am on my way to becoming?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Does that represent the kind of person I want to be?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Do I want to spend (a lot of) time with people like that?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If the answer to any of the last three is &#34;no&#34;, then it doesn&#39;t seem like it&#39;s the best place to go, no matter how prestigious, ego-boosting, or monetarily rewarding it may be.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>