<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Posts on Temporary Obsession</title>
    <link>http://temporary-obsessions.github.io/posts/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Posts on Temporary Obsession</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 05 Apr 2018 11:48:13 -0400</lastBuildDate>
    
        <atom:link href="http://temporary-obsessions.github.io/posts/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Who do you want to be?</title>
      <link>http://temporary-obsessions.github.io/posts/students-who-do-you-want-to-be/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 05 Apr 2018 11:48:13 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://temporary-obsessions.github.io/posts/students-who-do-you-want-to-be/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;A high school principal I know told a story told to her by another principal. It was approximately:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
A lot of students ask me what it takes to get into the National Honor Society. But one student stood out for asking a different question: &#34;What is it like to &lt;em&gt;be&lt;/em&gt; a member of the National Honor Society?&#34; (emphasis mine)
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This question bounced in my mind off something else I heard recently, on a college tour with one of my daughters. There, one of the admissions officials said something like:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Most of our students share the following three characteristics (what they were doesn&#39;t really matter). You don&#39;t have to have all three of these, or two of them, or even one. But you should want to be around people like that.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For students looking at colleges, or, in fact, for any of us looking at a new job with a new organization, or a new role of any kind, these questions provide a valuable way of thinking about what to do:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;What are the characteristics of the people involved?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Does that represent the kind of person I am on my way to becoming?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Does that represent the kind of person I want to be?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Do I want to spend (a lot of) time with people like that?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If the answer to any of the last three is &#34;no&#34;, then it doesn&#39;t seem like it&#39;s the best place to go, no matter how prestigious, ego-boosting, or monetarily rewarding it may be.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>